<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writings on Satbhav Voleti</title>
    <link>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Writings on Satbhav Voleti</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 11:19:08 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Note on Levinas and Heidegger</title>
      <link>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/heidegger-levinas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/heidegger-levinas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You can find a note on a quick comparison between Heidegger and what Levinas brings new to the table &lt;a href=&#34;../files/Heidegger-Levinas.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I made this note to really raise the question of how the overturning of ontology in favour of ethics affects logic (for context: Mohanty claims that Heidegger&amp;rsquo;s privileging of ontology over logic engenders a pre-theoretical discloure of being).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Note on Levinas and Heidegger</title>
      <link>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/marx/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/marx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My dear friend, &lt;a href=&#34;https://adityadwarkesh.github.io&#34;&gt;Aditya&lt;/a&gt;, and I made some elementary notes on Allen Wood&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;em&gt;Karl Marx&lt;/em&gt;. We finished approximately half of it and summarized the sections on alienation, (the fascinating and perplexing notion) &lt;em&gt;Gattungswesen&lt;/em&gt; and historical materialism. You can find them &lt;a href=&#34;../files/Heidegger-Levinas.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experimenter&#39;s Regress</title>
      <link>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/experimentersregress/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/experimentersregress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While attending the brilliant workshop, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.philsciindia.com/&#34;&gt;PhilSciIndia&lt;/a&gt; 2021, I presented an application of Nyāya responses to Nāgārjuna&amp;rsquo;s version of the problem of criterion to modern skepticism about experimental apparatus (by the sociologist Harry Collins). The idea was to recreate a reliabilist account of scientific epistemology for experiments. You can find the presentation &lt;a href=&#34;../files/Experimenter&#39;s%20Regress.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Short History of Analytic Philosophy of Language</title>
      <link>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/analyticphillanguage/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/analyticphillanguage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I made a (criminally) short &lt;a href=&#34;../files/Short%20History%20of%20Philosophy%20of%20Language.pdf&#34;&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt; for a discussion session on analytic philosophy of language, focusing on the second half of the twentieth century–Quine, Wittgenstein, Davidson, Lewis, Kripke, Putnam, Dummett, Grice and Austin. It is fairly amateurish and incredibly compressed but gives a highlights tour of the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gödel&#39;s Incompleteness Theorems - An Interdisclipinary Review</title>
      <link>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/godel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/godel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My dear friend, Aditya Dwarkesh (you can find him &lt;a href=&#34;https://adityadwarkesh.github.io&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and I wrote an expository article on Gödel&amp;rsquo;s Incompleteness Theorems and their colourful reception in the philosophical and mathematical circles of their time. We discuss the immediate reception by Zermelo, Wittgenstein and others, as well as the philosophical fallout of the theorems in various fields—philosophy of mathematics, information theory and philosophy of mind. This article was published in the Indian Science Cruiser in 2021. You can find the article &lt;a href=&#34;../files/Godel&#39;s%20Incompleteness%20Theorems.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
As a supplement to this article, we presented a &lt;a href=&#34;../files/Incompleteness%20Poster.pdf&#34;&gt;poster&lt;/a&gt; of a rigorous proof of the theorems on the Mathematics &amp;amp; Statistics Department Day at IISER-Kolkata.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Western Modern Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/earlymodernwestern/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://satbhavvoleti.github.io/writings/earlymodernwestern/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While reading various early modern texts of Europe, I made some (highly unoriginal) &lt;a href=&#34;../files/Western%20Modern%20Philosophy.pdf&#34;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt; by an almost collage method; pulling from many secondaries on major figures of the time period. The notes are highly incomplete and are a slow work in progress, but the main sources were Jeffrey Tlumak&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Classical Modern Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;, Dan Garber&amp;rsquo;s work on Decartes, and Michael Ayer&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Locke: Epistemology and Ontology&lt;/em&gt;. Maybe they can be of some help for skimming through before an exam?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
